She wrote:
كتبَت:
"When I become famous, I will tell everyone
"عندما أصبح مشهورةً، سأخبر الجميع
that I know a hero named Marlon Peterson."
أني أعرف بطلاً اسمه (مارلون بيترسون)."
Heroes rarely look like me.
نادراً ما يبدو الأبطال مثلي.
In fact,
في الحقيقة،
I'm what garbage looks like.
أنا ما تبدو عليه القمامة.
No, not the most appealing way to open a talk
لا، ليست الطريقة الأكثر جاذبية لفتح حديث
or start a conversation,
أو بدء حوار،
and perhaps you have some questions going through your head about that.
وربما هناك بعض الأسئلة التي تدور في ذهنكم حيال ذلك.
Why would this man say such a thing about himself?
لماذا قد يقول هذا الرجل شيئاً كهذا عن نفسه؟
What does he mean?
ما الذي يعنيه؟
How can someone view him as a hero when he sees himself as garbage?
كيف يمكن لأحد أن يراه بطلاً و هو يرى نفسه قمامة؟
I believe we learn more from questions than we do from answers.
أعتقد أننا نتعلم من الأسئلة أكثر مما نتعلم من الإجابات.
Because when we're questioning something,
لأننا عندما نتساءل عن أمر ما،
we're invested in taking in some sort of new information,
نكون عازمين على أخذ معلومات جديدة،
or grappling with some sort of ignorance that makes us feel uncomfortable.
أو أن نتصارع مع جهل يشعرنا بعدم الارتياح.
And that's why I'm here:
و لهذا أنا هنا:
to push us to question,
لأدفع بسؤال نحونا،
even when it makes us uncomfortable.
حتى و إن كان يشعرنا بعدم الارتياح.
My parents are from Trinidad and Tobago,
والداي من (ترينيداد و توباغو)
the southernmost island in the Caribbean.
جزيرة في أقصى جنوب البحر الكاريبي.
Trinidad is also home to the only acoustic instrument
(ترينيداد) أيضاً موطن للأداة الصوتية الوحيدة
invented in the 20th century:
التي تم اختراعها في القرن العشرين:
the steel pan.
صفيحة الفولاذ
Deriving from the African drums
منحدرةً من الطبول الأفريقية
and evolving from the genius of one of the ghettos in Trinidad,
و مطورة بعبقرية إحدى الأحياء الفقيرة في (ترينيداد)،
a city called Laventille,
مدينة تسمى (لافنتيل)،
and the disregard of the American military ...
و إهمال الجيش الأميريكي ...
Well, I should tell you,
حسنا،يجب أن أخبركم،
America, during WWII, had military bases set up in Trinidad,
نصبت أمريكا، خلال الحرب العالمية الثانية، قواعد عسكرية في (ترينيداد)،
and when the war ended,
وعندما انتهت الحرب،
they left the island littered with empty oil drums --
تركوا الجزيرة بعد أن بعثروا فيها براميل نفط فارغة --
their trash.
قمامتهم.
So people from Laventille repurposed the old drums left behind
لذا قام سكان (لافنتيل) بإعادة استخدام براميل النفط القديمة المتروكة
into the full chromatic scale:
في نطاق صوتي كامل:
the steel pan.
الصفيحة الفولاذية.
Playing music now from Beethoven to Bob Marley to 50 Cent,
بعزفهم الموسيقى من (بيتهوفن) مروراً بـ (بوب مارلي) إلى (فيفتي سنت)،
those people literally made music out of garbage.
قام هؤلاء الناس حرفياً بصنع موسيقى من القمامة.
Twelve days before my 20th birthday,
اثني عشر يوماً قبل عيد ميلادي العشرين،
I was arrested for my role in a violent robbery attempt
اعتقلت لمشاركتي في محاولة سطو مسلح
in lower Manhattan.
في جنوب (منهاتن).
While people were sitting in a coffee shop,
بينما كان الناس جالسين في مقهى،
four people were shot.
تم إطلاق النار على أربعة أشخاص.
Two were killed.
قتل إثنان.
Five of us were arrested.
واعتقل خمسة منا.
We were all the products of Trinidad and Tobago.
كنا جميعاً من (ترينيداد وتوباغو).
We were the "bad immigrants,"
كنا "اللاجئين السيئين"
or the "anchor babies" that Trump and millions of Americans easily malign.
أو "أطفال لوالدين غير أمريكيين" الذين
I was discarded, like waste material --
تم التخلص مني كالمخلفات
I eventually served 10 years, two months and seven days of a prison sentence.
أمضيت عشر سنوات وشهرين وسبع أيام كعقوبة سجن
I was sentenced to a decade of punishment in a correctional institution.
حكم علي بعقد من العقاب في مؤسسة إصلاحية.
I was sentenced to irrelevance --
حكم علي بعدم الإنتماء
the opposite of humanity.
ضد الإنسانية،
Interestingly,
وللغرابة،
it was during those years in prison that a series of letters redeemed me,
تلك الرسائل التي خلصتني كانت خلال سنوات السجن
helped me move beyond the darkness and the guilt
ساعدتني لأتخطى الظلمة والذنب
associated with the worst moment of my young life.
الآتيان من أسوأ لحظة من حياتي الشابة.
It gave me a sense that I was useful.
أعطتني شعوراً بأني مفيد.
She was 13 years old.
كانت بعمر 13 سنة.
She had wrote that she saw me as a hero.
وكتبت أنها تراني كبطل.
I remember reading that,
أتذكر قراءة ذلك،
and I remember crying when I read those words.
أتذكر بكائي عندما قرأت هذه الكلمات
She was one of over 50 students
كانت واحدةً من أكثر من 50 طالب وطالبة.
and 150 letters that I wrote during a mentoring correspondence program
و 150 رسالة كتبتها خلال برنامج المراسلات الإرشادية
that I co-designed with a friend
الذي شاركت في تصميمه مع صديق لي
who was a teacher at a middle school in Brooklyn,
كان مدرساً في مدرسة متوسطة في (بروكلن)،
my hometown.
مدينتي.
We called it the Young Scholars Program.
سميناه برنامج العلماء الشباب.
Every time those young people shared their stories with me,
كل مرة يشاركني بها هولاء الشباب قصصهم،
their struggles,
معاناتهم،
every time they drew a picture of their favorite cartoon character
كل مرة يرسمون صورة لشخصيتهم الكرتونية المفضلة
and sent it to me,
ويرسلونها لي،
every time they said they depended on my letters or my words of advice,
كل مرة قالوا أنهم يعتمدون على رسائلي وكلماتي الناصحة،
it boosted my sense of worthiness.
عززت من شعوري بأن لي قيمة.
It gave me a sense of what I could contribute to this planet.
أعطتني شعوراً بما يمكن أن أقدم لهذا الكوكب.
It transformed my life.
حولت حياتي.
Because of those letters and what they shared with me,
بسبب هذه الرسائل وما شاركوه معي،
their stories of teen life,
قصص مراهقتهم،
they gave me the permission,
أعطوني إذناً،
they gave me the courage to admit to myself
أعطوني شجاعةً لأعترف لنفسي
that there were reasons -- not excuses --
بأنه كان هناك أسباب -- لا حجج --
but that there were reasons for that fateful day in October of 1999;
كان هنالك أسباب لذلك اليوم المصيري في أكتوبر 1999
that the trauma associated with living in a community
بأن الصدمة المرتبطة بالعيش في مجتمع
where guns are easier to get than sneakers;
شراء الأسلحة فيه أسهل من شراء حذاء رياضي.
that the trauma associated with being raped at gunpoint at the age of 14;
الصدمة المتعلقة بالإغتصاب بتهديد السلاح بعمر الـ 14
that those are reasons for me
كانت هذه أسباباً لي
why making that decision,
جعلت من اتخاذي لذلك القرار،
that fatal decision,
ذلك القرار المصيري،
was not an unlikely proposition.
عدم كونه افتراض غير متوقع.
Because those letters mattered so much to me,
لأن هذه الرسائل عنت الكثير لي،
because writing and receiving
لأن الكتابة والاستقبال
and having that communication with those folks
والتواصل مع هؤلاء الناس
so hugely impacted my life,
أثر على حياتي بقوة،
I decided to share the opportunity with some friends of mine
قررت أن أشارك فرصتي مع بعض أصدقائي
who were also inside with me.
الذين كانوا سجناء معي.
My friends Bill and Cory and Arocks,
أصدقائي (بيل) و (كوري) و (أيروكس)،
all in prison for violent crimes also,
كلهم في السجن بسبب جرائم عنف كذلك،
shared their words of wisdom with the young people as well,
شاركوا كلماتهم من الحكمة مع هؤلاء الشباب أيضاً،
and received the sense of relevancy in return.
وحصلوا على شعور بالإنتماء بالمقابل.
We are now published writers and youth program innovators
نحن الأن كتاب لهم مطبوعات ومطوري برامج للشباب
and trauma experts
وخبراء صدمات
and gun violence prevention advocates,
ودعاة لمنع عنف السلاح،
and TED talkers and --
ومتحدثي TED و --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and good daddies.
وأباء جيدون.
That's what I call a positive return of investment.
هذا ما أسمية عائد إيجابي لمجهود.
Above all else,
فوق هذا كله،
what building that program taught me was that when we sow,
ما تعلمته من بناء هذا البرنامج أنه عندما رأينا،
when we invest in the humanity of people no matter where they're at,
عندما نستثمر في إنسانية الأشخاص أينما كان موقعهم،
we can reap amazing rewards.
يممكننا أن نجني عوائد رائعة.
In this latest era of criminal justice reform,
في هذه الحقبة الأخيرة من إصلاح العدالة الجنائية
I often question and wonder why --
غالباً ما أتسائل وأفكر لماذا --
why is it that so many believe
لماذا يؤمن الكثيرون
that only those who have been convicted of nonviolent drug offenses
بأن فقط من حكم عليهم في جرائم مخدرات لم يستخدم فيها العنف
merit empathy and recognized humanity?
يستحقون الشفقة والاعتراف بإنسانيتهم؟
Criminal justice reform is human justice.
إصلاح القانون الجنائي هو عدالة إنسانية.
Am I not human?
ألست إنساناً؟
When we invest in resources that amplify the relevancy of people
عندما نوظف جهودنا في موارد تظهر دور الناس
in communities like Laventille
في المجتمعات مثل (لافنتيل)
or parts of Brooklyn or a ghetto near you,
أو أجزاء من(بروكلن) أو أي حي فقير بالقرب منكم،
we can literally create the communities that we want.
يمكننا حرفياً أن نصنح المجتمعات التي نريد.
We can do better.
يمكننا أن نقوم بما هو أفضل.
We can do better than investing solely in law enforcement as a resource,
يمكننا أن نفعل أفضل من الإجتهاد في تطبيق القانون كمصدر وحيد،
because they don't give us a sense of relevancy
لأنه لا يعطينا إحساساً بالإنتماء
that is at the core of why so many of us do so many harmful things
وهذا هو جوهر كون الكثير منا يقوم بأفعال مؤذية
in the pursuit of mattering.
في السعي وراء الأهمية.
See, gun violence is just a visible display of a lot of underlying traumas.
أترون، العنف المسلح هو فقط الطبقة الظاهرة لما يختبئ تحتها من الصدمات.
When we invest in the redemptive value of relevancy,
عندما نوظف جهودنا في تخليص هذه القيمة من الإنتماء،
we can render a return of both personal responsibility and healing.
يمكننا أن نقدم المساعدة لعودة المسؤولية الشخصية وبدء الشفاء.
That's the people work I care about,
هذا عمل الناس الذي أهتم به،
because people work.
لأن الناس تعمل.
Family, I'm asking you to do the hard work,
أيتها الأسرة، أطلب منكم أن تقوموا بالعمل الشاق،
the difficult work,
العمل الصعب،
the churning work of bestowing undeserved kindness
العمل المتمخض عن منح إحسان غير مستحق
upon those who we can relegate as garbage,
لهؤلاء الذين ندنيهم لمستوى القمامة
who we can disregard and discard easily.
الذين يمكننا أن نتجاهلهم وننبذهم بسهولة.
I'm asking myself.
أسأل نفسي.
Over the past two months,
خلال الشهرين الماضيين،
I've lost two friends to gun violence,
خسرت اثنين من أصدقائي في أعمال عنف مسلح،
both innocent bystanders.
كلاهما أبرياء لم يقوما بشيء.
One was caught in a drive-by while walking home.
أحدهما أطلق عليه النار من سيارة بينما كان يمشي نحو منزله
The other was sitting in a café while eating breakfast,
والآخر كان يجلس في مقهى يتناول إفطاره،
while on vacation in Miami.
خلال إجازته في (ميامي).
I'm asking myself to see the redemptive value of relevancy
أطلب من نفسي أن أرى قيمة الخلاص في الإنتماء
in the people that murdered them,
في هؤلاء الناس الذين قتلوهم،
because of the hard work of seeing the value in me.
بسبب العمل الشاق الذي بذلته لأراها في نفسي
I'm pushing us to challenge our own capacity
أنا أدفع بنا لتحدي طاقاتنا
to fully experience our humanity,
أن نتعايش تماماً مع إنسانيتنا،
by understanding the full biography
من خلال فهم السيرة الكاملة
of people who we can easily choose not to see,
لأشخاص بإمكاننا بسهولة أن نختار أن لا نراهم،
because heroes are waiting to be recognized,
لأن الأبطال ينتظرون أن يتم التعرف عليهم،
and music is waiting to be made.
والموسيقى بانتظار أن تصنع.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)